Guide to the Lincoln Ellsworth Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lincoln Ellsworth Papers
1921-1928
MS 1311
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, unpublished writings, awards, memorabilia, and maps relating to Lincoln Ellsworth's flight across the North Pole in 1926. Included also is a copy of P. Kühne's: Chamois-Hunting in Switzerland, with the original drawings and correspondence of Arthur Frost. Principal correspondents are Roald Amundsen, Richard E. Byrd, Calvin Coolidge, Wilbur Cross, Charles Dawes, Frank Kellogg, and Theodore Roosevelt.
Ellsworth, Lincoln, 1880-1951
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Lincoln Ellsworth, 1956.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of papers relating to Lincoln Ellsworth's flight across the North Pole in 1926 with Roald Amundsen and Umberto Nobile. Included are correspondence, various unpublished writings by Ellsworth, the certificate of award of the Norwegian Order of St. Olav, several maps, memorabilia, and other miscellaneous papers such as P. Kühne's "Chamois-Hunting in Switzerland" with the original drawings and correspondence of Arthur Frost bound in.
In the correspondence, along with letters of congratulations and announcements of awards and honors for Ellsworth, are numerous letters from Amundsen dealing with business matters such as the publication of their book First Crossing of the Polar Sea (a typescript can be found in the collection) and the awards of the Order of St. Olav, and with a controversy over the extent of Nobile's participation in the expedition. Also included in the correspondence are letters from Charles Dawes promoting the awards of a Congressional Medal to Ellsworth. Other notable correspondents are Richard E. Byrd, Calvin Coolidge, Wilbur Cross, Frank Kellogg, and Theodore Roosevelt. Much of the correspondence is addressed to persons other than Ellsworth.
All of the materials except the bound volumes came to Yale in the form of a portfolio compiled by Ellsworth and titled "Two Years of Arctic Exploration: Personal papers of Lincoln Ellsworth, 1925-1926." The porfolio has been dismantled for preservation purposes. The papers were the gift of Mrs. Lincoln Ellsworth in 1956.
Biographical / Historical
Lincoln Ellsworth, explorer and civil engineer, participated in the first Grand Pacific Railroad survey across Canada from 1902-1907. He worked as an engineer in Canada and Alaska from 1907-1924. In 1924, Ellsworth organized an expedition through the Andes to the Amazon River. In 1926, he participated in trans-polar flights and, in 1931, he participated in trans-Arctic flights and submarine expeditions. Ellsworth a made flight to the interior of Antarctica in 1939. He was the recipient of many awards and the author of several books.
Arctic regions -- Aerial exploration; North Pole -- Discovery and exploration; Drawings (visual works); Explorers; Amundsen, Roald, 1872-1928; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933; Cross, Wilbur L. (Wilbur Lucius), 1862-1948; Dawes, Charles Gates, 1865-1951; Ellsworth, Lincoln, 1880-1951; Kellogg, Frank B. (Frank Billings), 1856-1937; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1924-1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 6)
  - Writings:
    - "Infinitely Great and Infinitely Small", 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "News From the Stars", 1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Substance of Nature", 1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "The First Crossing of the Polar Sea, May 11th-13th, 1926. Official Narrative by Roald Amundsen and Lincoln Ellsworth" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Address, 1926 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Certificates, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorabilia, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - P. Kühne: "Chamois-Hunting in Switzerland" (original drawings and correspondence of Arthur B. Frost mounted and bound in) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1925-1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Additional Material, Circa early 1900s; Accession 1996-M-151
  - Photographs [the majority of photographs are not identified but appear to be of wildlife indigenous to the Great Plains region, such as buffalo and Rocky Mountain goats; hunting parties; and scenic views], Circa early 1900s (Box 1)